<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Devil was and is the old informer against the righteous</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30471</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11327482</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11327482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1188:21 or 1460:53)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Devil was and is the old informer against the righteous</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682/3 [i.e. 1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: G. Fox.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>This work appears on reel 1188:21 and 1460:53.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Harvard University Library and the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Devil.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47476:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DEVIL Was and Is the Old Informer AGAINST THE RIGHTEOUS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <p>HE that is an <hi>Informer,</hi> is a Perſecutor, and Spoiler, and a Deſtroyer; and the DEVIL is the Head of all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, Perſecutors and Deſtroyers of the RIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEOUS.</p>
            <p>He is an Adverſary of the Happineſs of all God's People, and an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of them: He is a Serpent, an Enemy to all that which is good: See his Emnity againſt <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and againſt their Happineſs, how it did appear againſt <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſee his Enmity in the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> who vexed Juſt and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lot</hi>'s Soul from day to day: and <hi>Noah,</hi> a Preacher of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to the old ungodly World, who did not regard him, no more than <hi>Sodom</hi> did <hi>Lot;</hi> but the one was drowned, and the other was turned into Aſhes.</p>
            <p>And ſee the Serpent's Enmity in the <hi>Jews,</hi> and in <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi> and what became of them who would have ſtoned him?</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47476:2"/>
            <p>And you may ſee the Enmity of the Serpent in the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ophets: and did not both the ten Tribes and the two Tribes go into Captivity for diſobeying the Lord? like their Father <hi>Adam</hi> in their Enmity againſt his Prophets and righteous People.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe you may ſee the Enmity of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erpent in the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt Chriſt and his Apoſtles, inſomuch that Chriſt called the <hi>Jews, Serpents, and of their Father the Devil:</hi> and what became of thoſe <hi>Jews?</hi> were they not ſcatter'd among all Nations, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and their Place of Worſhip deſtroyed?</p>
            <p>And what Condition is all Chriſtendom in, that is erred from the Holy Ghoſt and Power the Apoſtles were in? have they not received the unclean ghoſt or ſoul ſpirit of the Devil, the Enmity, Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, Accuſer and Deſtroyer, that old Informer, that makes them to deſtroy one another, makes them to envy and accuſe, and Informers, and Deſtroyers of the Righteous? And that ſoul ſpirit or unclean ghoſt hath brought Chriſtendom all on heaps, one againſt another, that are not in the Spirit and Power of Chriſt the Apoſtles were in.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Iob,</hi> chap. 1, 2. there you may ſee, the Devil and Satan, who was the Enmity and Murderer, appeared againſt <hi>Iob</hi> and his Sons and Daughters, to the ſpoiling of his Goods, yea and his Wife, who ſaid unto <hi>Iob, Curſe God and dye;</hi> but <hi>Iob</hi> called her, <hi>A fooliſh Woman,</hi> and did not ſin with his Lips, though he loſt his Sons and Daughters, and his Goods, and was ſtript of all; and though the Devill, Satan, ſaid unto the Lord, <hi>If that he would put his hand againſt</hi> Job, Job <hi>would curſe him to his face,</hi> Chap. 1. ver. 11.</p>
            <p>And again, Satan the Informer ſaid, <hi>Skin for skin, yea all that a man hath, will he give for his Life; but put forth thine Hand now, and touch his Bone, and Fleſh, and he will Curſe thee to thy face, Job.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>But in all theſe falſe Informations of the Devill, who was a murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and a Lyar from the beginning, and ſo was proved and manifeſt to be both a murderer, and a lyar and a falſe accuſer; for <hi>Job</hi> bleſſed the Lord, and did not ſin with his Lips, <hi>Iob</hi> 1, 2. Chapters.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Iob's</hi> Friends were miſerable Comforters; for the Lord ſaid, <hi>His Wrath was kindled againſt them: for they had not ſpoken right of the Lord, as his Servant</hi> Iob <hi>had;</hi> and therefore <hi>Iob</hi> was to pray to the Lord for them; and the Lord heard <hi>Iob</hi>'s Prayer for them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> miſtris was a wicked Informer, to her husband, againſt innocent <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> firſt ſhe Informed the men of her houſe, then ſhe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med her husband, whoſe wrath was kindled againſt him, that he took him, and caſt him into priſon. And all this was becauſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47476:2"/>would not yeild unto his Miſtriſs's wickedneſs, and Sin againſt God; ſo here was the Serpent, and the Devil, the adverſary, appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Innocent <hi>Joſeph</hi> whom God was withal, and made him to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>But in <hi>Proverbs</hi> 7. you may ſee, how the Woman, with the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire of a Harlot, and ſubtilty of heart, whoſe feet abides not in her Houſe, and lieth in wait, in every Corner of the Street, in Twie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Evening, in the black and dark Night, deceived the Young Man, void of underſtanding; for they that have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, will ſhun her; for by the means of a Whoriſh Woman, a man is brought to a piece of Bread, and the Adulterous will hunt for the precious Life of the Righteous.</p>
            <p>And though the Informers, and Archers, did ſorely grieve <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and ſhot at him, and hated him, yet his bow abode in ſtrength, and <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren did envie him for his Dream, but his Father <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> obſerved his ſayings.</p>
            <p>And you may ſee how <hi>Pharoah</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> informed his People, the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> againſt the <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> and ſet Task-Maſters over them, that made their lives bitter; and the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Task-Maſters obeyed <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Commands, and made them to make Brick without Straw, and ſerve with Rigour: But the <hi>Hebrew-Midwives</hi> would not obey <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> to kill the Men-Children; and the more <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Task-Maſters perſecuted and oppreſt them, the more they Multiplyed, But what became of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and all his Perſecutors and Informers at Laſt? Did not God overthrow them in the Sea, and deliver his People?</p>
            <p>There Ran a Young man, and told <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Illdad,</hi> and <hi>Madad were Prophecying in the Camp:</hi> and one ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> My Lord forbid them; and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid unto him; <hi>Envieſt thou for my ſake? would God that all the Lords People were Prophets; and that the Lord mould put his Spirit upon them,</hi> Numb. 11.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Moſes</hi> did not give Credit, to thoſe Informers, but rather reproved them, &amp; encouraged the <hi>Prophets,</hi> deſiring that all the Lords People were <hi>Prophets.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> was far off from ſaying have them before a Magiſtrate, and Fine them 20 l. apiece, for ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And what became of all thoſe that went to ſearch the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and brought an evil report upon the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God's promiſe, and to <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> that theſe falſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47476:3"/>Informers made the Congregation ſo envious, that they were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſtone <hi>Moſes?</hi> and did not thoſe falſe Informers, and them that joyned with them, their Carcaſſes fall in the Wilderneſs? Numb. 14. And what became of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and the 250. Princes, that were famous in the Congregation, and men of renown, which told <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Congregation were holy, every one of them; for the Lord is among them: wherefore them lift you up your ſelves above the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord.</hi> See what high words theſe Informers could ſpeak, to inſenſe the Congregation againſt <hi>Moſe.</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſuch as feared God. Did not the Earth ſwallow up <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company alive? and did not a Fire come from the Lord, and conſume the 259 And on the morrow all the Congregation of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> murmured againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and told him, <hi>He had killed the people of the Lord:</hi> Did not the Wrath of the Lord go out againſt them, and there dyed of the Plauge 1470 of them; So here was the End of thoſe murmurers, or Informers, and Rebels againſt the Lord, his Truth and People; <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>And again, you may ſee what <hi>Moah</hi> ſaid unto the Elders of <hi>Median</hi> againſt the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Balack</hi> ſent the Elders of <hi>Moah,</hi> and the Elde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of <hi>Median,</hi> to <hi>Balaam</hi> with Rewards of Divination in their hands, to Curſe the <hi>Jews,</hi> the People of God; but the Lord for bad <hi>Balaam</hi> to Curſe them, though <hi>Balaam</hi> loved the Rewards of Unrighteouſneſs: and <hi>Balack</hi> ſent yet again Princes more honourable than the firſt Elders; and <hi>Balack</hi> told <hi>Balaam, He would promote him to great Honour, if he would Curſe the Children of</hi> Iſrael. But ſee what came upon <hi>Balaam;</hi> his Aſs reproved him, and the Lord made him to ſpeak that which confounded <hi>Balaam:</hi> and after was not <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> and the <hi>Medionites</hi> deſtroyed? <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. &amp; 31. Here you may ſee how the Enemy appeared in <hi>Balack,</hi> who would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the <hi>Jews?</hi> but the Lord prevented him, and <hi>Balaam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And many Informers were againſt <hi>David,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>Doedg</hi> the <hi>Edomite,</hi> which informed <hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the Prieſt, and all his Father's houſe, becauſe he received <hi>David:</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> commanded his Foot-men to ſlay the Prieſts; but <hi>Saul</hi>'s Servants would not put forth their Hands to fall upon the Prieſts of the Lord; and <hi>Saul</hi> bid <hi>Doedg</hi> the <hi>Edomite,</hi> the Informer, and he fell upon them, and ſlew eighty five perſons on that day, that wore the Linnen Ephod
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47476:3"/>and <hi>Noh,</hi> the City of the Prieſts, ſmote he with the edge of the Sword, both Men, Women, Children and Sucklings. And here you may ſee the Informer was a Murderer of the Innocent, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. And in chap. 23, 25, 26. you may ſee how the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers went to <hi>Saul,</hi> and informed him againſt <hi>David.</hi> And you may ſee in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52. how <hi>David</hi> propheſied the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Doedg</hi> the <hi>Edomite,</hi> who came and told <hi>Saul,</hi> and ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, David <hi>is come in the houſe of</hi> Ahimelec.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. there you may ſee ſeveral Informers writ Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Artaxerces,</hi> to hinder the building of the City <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And you may ſee how buſie <hi>Tobiah,</hi> and the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and the <hi>Amonites,</hi> and <hi>Aſhdodites,</hi> and <hi>Sanbalat</hi> were aganſt the <hi>Jews</hi> when they built <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and how that <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanbalat</hi> hired the Falſe Prophets to Propheſie againſt <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah;</hi> but their Prophecies &amp; their works came to nought; for the Lord helped his People againſt them, whom the Serpent made Enemies, and Adverſaries, and Informers againſt them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Hamon,</hi> that great Informer againſt <hi>Mordecai</hi> &amp; the <hi>Jews; Hamon</hi> ſaid unto King <hi>Ahaſuerus, there is a certain people ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed abroad in all the Province of thy Kingdom, and their Laws are diverſe from all people, neither keep they the King's Laws; therefore it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them: if it pleaſe the King, let it be written, that they may be deſtroyed, and I will pay Ten thouſand talents of ſilver to the hands of thoſe that have the charge of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to bring it into the King's Treaſuries.</hi> Now here you may ſee the Devil, the Deſtroyer, who is the Enemy &amp; adverſary of God's People, how this Informer hath exceeded all the Informers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and all the Informers in our times; for inſtead of being an Informer to get Money; he would give the King Money to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy God's People, yea 10000. Talents of Silver; and he got the Kings Seal for it too, to ſeal his Writing; but for all this, what became of <hi>Hamon?</hi> Was not he hanged on the Gallows which he built for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> &amp; aboundance of his confederates deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And there was the End of proud <hi>Hamon</hi> whom the deſtroyer led to be an Informer, and a deſtroyer, who was deſtroyed upon the Gallows that he built for another.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Jer.</hi> 38. <hi>Paſhur,</hi> with many others, were Informers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> to <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the King; and you may ſee this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhur,</hi> the Son of a Prieſt, had put <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the Stocks, and ſmote
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47476:4"/>him; and the envious Informers ſaid unto <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> whom the Devil ſtirred up to murder him, <hi>We beſeech thee, O King, let</hi> Jeremiah <hi>be put to death; for he weakens the hands of the men of war, that remain in the City, &amp; the hands of all the people, in ſpeaking ſuch words unto them; for</hi> Jeremiah <hi>ſeeks not the welfare of this people, but their hurt:</hi> then <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>He is in your hands; for the King is not he, that can do any thing againſt you.</hi> Then they took <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and let him down with Cords into the Dungeon, &amp; he ſunk in the Mire; and the <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> one of the King's Eunuchs, told the King what theſe Informe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s had done, and how that <hi>Ieremiah</hi> would dye in the Dungeon; and the King bid him <hi>take thirty men with him, and take up</hi> Jeremiah <hi>before he dyed;</hi> and the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> took old clouts &amp; rotten raggs, &amp; let them down by Cords into the Dungeon, &amp; bid him <hi>tye them under his Arm-holes,</hi> &amp; ſo he drew him out of the Dungeon, and put him into the Court of the Priſon, where he remained till <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was taken by <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzer,</hi> who put <hi>Jeremiah</hi> out of Priſon, &amp; gave him Liberty; and ſo he found more mercy at the hands of the <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> and <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzer</hi>'s Officers, than he did among the profeſſing <hi>Jews,</hi> the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: And you may ſee what a Deſtruction came upon the City, <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and his Sons, and his men of War, and his people, for diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Word of the Lord: And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> told the <hi>Athiopian,</hi> that helpt him out of the Dungeon, <hi>That he ſhould not fall by</hi> Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzer's <hi>Sword, becauſe he put his truſt in the Lord,</hi> Jer. 39.</p>
            <p>So here was the End of theſe Informers, carried into <hi>Babylon,</hi> and many deſtroyed. And you may ſee how the Devil, the Murderer, and his Informers, his Perſecutors that put <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the Dungeon, and thought to have taken away his Life, were put into Priſon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and many of their lives loſt; and <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> who was faithful, and truſted the Lord, ſaved, <hi>Jer.</hi> 39, &amp; 40.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. you may ſee how the deſtroyer raiſed up Informers againſt the three Children, and went to the King, and accuſed the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Thou O King haſt made a Decree, that every man ſhould fall down, and worſhip the Golden Image; and whoſo falleth not down, and worſhippeth, he ſhall be caſt in a Fiery Furnace; there are certain</hi> Jews (ſaid they) <hi>which are ſet over the Affairs of the Province of</hi> Babylon, Shadrach, Meſhech, <hi>and</hi> Abednego; <hi>thoſe men, O King, have not regarded thee, they ſerve not thy Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which thou haſt ſet up:</hi> This ſaid the Informers. Then <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzer</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47476:4"/>in his Rage and Fury commanded to bring <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> before him, and he ſaid unto them, <hi>Is it true? do you not ſerve my Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which I have ſet up, &amp;c? but if you worſhip not, ye ſhall be caſt the ſame ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r into the midſt of the Fiery Furnace: Who is that God that ſhall deliver you out of my hands?</hi> Then ſaid the three Children unto the King, <hi>We are not careful to anſwer thee in this matter; but if it be ſo, our God, whom we ſerve is able to deliver us from the burning Fiery Furnace; and he will deliver us out of thy hands, O King: But if not, be it known to thee, O King, we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi> Here was a poſitive Anſwer, and a Godly Confidence. <hi>Then was the King full of Fury, and the form of his Viſage was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt the three Children; and he commanded his Furnace to be heat ſeven times more than it was wont to be, and commanded his moſt mighty men of his Army to bind the three Children in their Coats, Hoſe and Hats, and other Garments, and caſt them into the midſt of the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Furnace; which Flames of Fire ſlew thoſe men that caſt them in: Then the King was aſtoniſhed, and roſe up in haſte, and ſaid unto his Counſellors, Did not we caſt three men bound in the midſt of the Fire? And they anſwered, and ſaid unto the Knig, True O King: And he anſwered and ſaid, Lo I ſee four men looſe, walking in the midſt of the Fire, and they have no hurt, and the form of the fourth is like the Son of God: and the King called the three Children out of the Fire.</hi> And ſo the King was made to bleſs the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Abednego;</hi> and made a Decree, <hi>That every People, Nation and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which ſpoke any thing amiſs againſt the God of</hi> Sadrach, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech <hi>&amp;</hi> Abednego, <hi>ſhall be cut in pieces, &amp; their Houſes ſhall be made a Dunghill, becauſe there is no other God that can deliver after this ſort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here you may ſee, the Lord confounded the Murderous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, and the Fury and Rage of <hi>Nebuchadnezzer;</hi> and his Mighty men were ſlain, that caſt the three Children into the Fire; but the Lord delivered the three Children that truſted in him, to the Exaltation of his Glory and Name.</p>
            <p>And alſo you may ſee in <hi>Daniel</hi> 6. <hi>Darius</hi> made <hi>Daniel</hi> chief of the Preſidents, and the Preſidents and Princes turned Informers againſt <hi>Daniel;</hi> and theſe Informers could not find any fault or Error in him, becauſe he was faithful; then ſaid theſe Informers, <hi>We ſhall not find any occaſion againſt this</hi> Daniel, <hi>except we find it againſt him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47476:5"/>the Law of his God.</hi> And therefore they got the King to eſtabliſh a Decree in writing, that it be not changed, according to the Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which alters not; which <hi>Decree</hi> was, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould ask a Petition of any God or Man for thirty days, ſaving of thee, O King, they ſhall be caſt into the Den of Lyons. And all the Preſidents of the Kingdom, and the Governours, and the Princes, and the Counſellors, and the Captains, conſulted together concerning this Decree, which the King ſigned. Now</hi> Daniel <hi>knew the Writing was ſigned; he went to his Houſe, and his Windows being open in his Chamber, &amp;c. he kneeled down three times of the day, &amp; pray'd and gave thanks to God, as he had done before time.</hi> Then theſe men, the Informers, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and found <hi>Daniel</hi> praying, and making ſupplication before his God; then theſe men aſſembled unto the King, and informed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Daniel;</hi> then the King commanded <hi>Daniel</hi> to be brought, and be caſt into the Lyons Den, according to the Decree that they had wickedly got of the King; and the King encouraged <hi>Daniel,</hi> and ſaid unto him, <hi>Thy God, whom thou ſerveſt, he will deliver thee:</hi> and early in the morning the King roſe, and went in haſte unto the Den of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſaid, <hi>O</hi> Daniel, <hi>the Servant of the living God, is thy God, whom thou ſerveſt continually, able to deliver thee?</hi> And <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid, <hi>My God hath ſent his Angel, and ſhut up the Lyons Mouthes, that they have not hurt me, foraſmuch as before him Innocency was found in me, and alſo before thee, O King, I have done no hurt.</hi> And then the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to take up <hi>Daniel</hi> out of the Lyons Den; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to take thoſe great men, which were the Accuſers and Informers againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> and caſt them, and their Wives and Children into the Lyons Den; and the Lyons had the maſtery over them, and broke all their Bones in pieces or ever they came at the bottom of the Den. So here was the end of theſe deviliſh Informers, or Accuſers, who were Princes and Preſidents. And then <hi>Darius</hi> made a Decree, <hi>That in every Dominion of his Kingdom, men tremble and fear before the God of</hi> Daniel; <hi>for he is the Living God, and ſteadfaſt forever, and his Kingdom that which ſhall not be deſtroyed, and his Dominion ſhall be even to the end.</hi> Here you may ſee, God was exalted by them that believed in him, and the wicked deſtroying Informers were deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And the Chief Prieſts and Scribes ſought how they might kill <hi>Jeſus,</hi> for they feared the people; then entred Satan into <hi>Iudas,</hi> and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muned with the Chief Prieſts and Captains, <hi>how he might betray him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47476:5"/>unto them;</hi> and they were glad, and covenanted with him to give him Money (to wit) thirty pieces of Silver; and the Chief Prieſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the multitude, that they ſhould ask <hi>Barrabas,</hi> and cruci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie <hi>Ieſus;</hi> and all the Chief Prieſts and Elders of the people took coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel againſt Jeſus to put him to death; and they ſought Falſe Witneſſes againſt him, but found none; at the laſt came two Falſe Witneſſes, and ſaid, <hi>This Fellow ſaid, I am able to deſtroy the Temple of God, and build it in three days:</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> ſought to releaſe Jeſus; but the <hi>Iews</hi> cryed oat, <hi>If thou let this man go, thou art nor</hi> Caeſar's <hi>Friend &amp;c.</hi> And ſo when theſe Falſe Accuſers, and Informers, and Falſe witneſſes, with <hi>Pilat</hi>'s Judgment, had crucified Jeſus; after he was riſen, the Chief Prieſts aſſembled with the Elders, and after they had taken Counſel, they gave large Money to the Soldiers that watched the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, to ſay, That <hi>Chriſt's Diſciples came by Night, and ſtole him away while they ſlept.</hi> So here is the Devil and Satan, which entred into the <hi>Iews,</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> &amp;c. which made <hi>Iudas</hi> a Betrayer, and the <hi>Iews</hi> Falſe Witneſſes, Lyars and Murderers of the Juſt; and the <hi>Iews</hi> to this day believe their Lyes, and falſe Information, That Chriſt's Diſciples ſtole him away by Night while the Watch ſlept; but the Lord recompenced them all according to their Works.</p>
            <p>And you may ſee how Satan made Falſe Witneſſes and Informers againſt <hi>Steven;</hi> and they brought him to the High Prieſts Court and there he examin'd him; but at laſt you may ſee they Murder'd him, and ſtoned him to death as he was calling upon God, and ſaying, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit,</hi> Acts 7.</p>
            <p>And did not <hi>Judas</hi> betray Chriſt with a Kiſs? And was not Chriſt led to <hi>Caiphas</hi> the High Prieſts Court, or Hall, where the Scribes and Elders were aſſembled, and the High Prieſt examin'd him in his Court until the Cock cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> twice? And did not the Truth that Chriſt ſpoke to the High Prieſt put him into ſuch a Wrath or Rage, that he tore or rent his Clothes?</p>
            <p>And were not <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> haled before, <hi>Ananias</hi> the High Prieſts Court, where the Rulers, and Elders, and Scribes, and <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and many of the Kindred of the High Prieſt, were gathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed together? And did not they ſet <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> in the midſt, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min them, and charged them, <hi>to ſpeak no mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Name of Ieſus;</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you, or unto God, judg ye; for we cannot but ſpeak
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47476:6"/>the things which we have ſeen and heard;</hi> then the High Prieſt threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, and let them go. <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And again, you may ſee how the High Prieſt, and all that were with him, were ſilled with Indignation, and roſe up againſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and caſt them into the common Priſon; but the Lord deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</p>
            <p>And you may ſee all along in many places of <hi>Acts,</hi> how the <hi>Jews</hi> roſe up againſt the Apoſtles; and how that one of the Officers came and told the Chief Prieſts and Captain, <hi>That the Apoſtles were preaching in the Temple, which they caſt into Priſon;</hi> and the Captain and the Officers brought them, and ſet them before the Council; and the High Prieſt and they took counſel to ſlay them; but <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>Refrain your ſelves from theſe men, and let them alone; for if this Work or this Counſel be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, you cannot overthrow it, leſt happily ye be found even to fight againſt God:</hi> And his Counſel ſwayed, and ſtopt the High Prieſt and his Court for Murdering of them,</p>
            <p>And <hi>Saul,</hi> he made Havock of the Church, entring into every houſe, and haling men and women, committing them to priſon; and <hi>Saul</hi> yet breatheth out Threatnings and Slaughters againſt the Diſciples of the Lord, and went to the High Prieſt, and deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of him Letters to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> to the Synagogues, <hi>If he found any of this way, whether they were men or women, he might bring them bound to</hi> Jeruſalem. So his Authority was from the Chief Prieſt, to perſecute; but Chriſt met him in the way, and told him; <hi>It was hard for him to kick againſt the Pricks;</hi> and ſaid unto him, Saul, Saul, <hi>Why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> For he was perſecuting Chriſt in his Members; and Chriſt converted him, and after ſome time ſent him to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> to Preach his Goſpel, where he was going to perſecute; but after many days that he had Preach't the Goſpel at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> there took counſel to kill him, and and they watch't night and day at the Gates to kill him; but the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt took <hi>Paul</hi> by night, and let him down by the Wall in a Basket, and ſo he ſcaped thoſe murdering Profeſſors; without Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, as you may ſee in <hi>Acts</hi> 9. So he that went to perſecute at <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> was perſecuted at <hi>Damaſcus</hi> for Preaching Chriſt, whom he was going to perſecute: And here you may ſee how the Perſecutors were Confounded.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Acts.</hi> 14. there you may ſee how the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> ſtir'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47476:6"/>up the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp; made their minds evil affected againſt the Brethren; and <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer withſtood <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to turn away the Deputy from the Faith. Here you may ſee the profeſſing <hi>Jews</hi> and the Sorcerer were found in one ſpirit; but the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſpiritually blind with evil, &amp; God ſtruck <hi>Elimas</hi> naturally blind: and the <hi>Jews,</hi> which were more than ſorty, that came to the Chief Prieſts &amp; Elders, and ſaid unto them, how <hi>that they had bound themſelves under a Curſe, that they would neither eat nor drink until they had killed</hi> Paul; and the Chief Prieſts and the Council were to mannage this matter for the Murderers; then they were to ſend to the Captain; that kept <hi>Paul</hi> a Priſoner, to bring him out of the Caſtle, which was his Priſon, to the Chief Prieſts and Elders, under a pretence, <hi>that they would enquire ſomething of him;</hi> and theſe Murderers were ready to Murder him, before ever he came near them: but the Captain of the Caſtle under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the thing, the Lord put it in his mind to ſend <hi>Paul</hi> away, by which the Innocent eſcap't the hands of theſe Murdering Informers and Lyars, which the Chief Prieſts and Counſel had a hand in; and <hi>Paul</hi> had more Mercy from the <hi>Roman Captain,</hi> than he had from the profeſſing <hi>Jews,</hi> and their Prieſts: And after a while <hi>Ananias</hi> the High Prieſt with the Elders, with a certain Orator, named <hi>Tertullus,</hi> informed the Governour <hi>Faelix</hi> againſt <hi>Paul;</hi> and after a great deal of dawbing &amp; plauſible expreſſions, as you may ſee in <hi>Acts</hi> 24. ſaid they, <hi>we have found this man a Peſtilent Fellow, a Mover of Sedition among all the</hi> Jews <hi>throughont the World, and a Ring-leader of the Sect f the Nazareans;</hi> and ſo after many grievous falſe Charges they laid againſt <hi>Paul, Paul</hi> had liberty to clear himſelf from their Lyes, and Slanders, and falſe Informations; and when they had kept <hi>Paul</hi> about two years in Priſon there, <hi>Feſtus</hi> came into the Province, then the High Prieſt and chief of the <hi>Jews</hi> informed him againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and deſired favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, <hi>that he would ſend for him to Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> lying in wait in the way to kill him; but <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>Which among you are able, go down to</hi> Caeſaria <hi>to accuſe this man;</hi> and when they came there, they laid many grievous Complaints againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> which they could not Prove; and ſo the Lord delivered him out of theſe Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerous Informers hands, though <hi>Feflus</hi> would have done the <hi>Jews</hi> a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as having <hi>Paul</hi> up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be judged there by him; but <hi>Paul</hi> appealing unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> prevented him, and the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the high Prieſt of their Deſign againſt him, as you may ſee in <hi>Acts</hi> 25. more at large.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:47476:7"/>
            <p>And what became of <hi>Jezebel,</hi> with her informing Letters, that ſhe wrote in <hi>Ahab's</hi> name, to the Elders and Nobles that were in the City, dwelling with <hi>Naboth,</hi> who bid them, <hi>Proclame a Faſt, and ſet up</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both <hi>on high among the People;</hi> and ſent two Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> before him, to bear witneſs againſt him, ſaying, <hi>Thou didſt Blaſpheme God and the King;</hi> and then carry him out, and ſtone him, that he may dye; and they did ſo, according to <hi>Iezebel</hi>'s Information; and when they had killed him, ſhe and her Husband took poſſeſſion of his Eſtate: but what Deſtruction came upon <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezebel,</hi> and all that took their part, as you may read the Sentence and Judgment? 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>And therfore let all Murderers, Informers, and Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> take heed, who ſeek the Deſtruction of the Righteous, in that they bring Deſtruction upon themſelves, as you may ſee all along in the Scriptures, what was the End of ſuch, whether they were high or low, Prieſt, Profeſſor or Prophane, the Righteous God ſpared none; and therefore read the Scriptures from on End of the Book to the other, &amp; here you may ſee the ſad Examples and Judgments that have come on ſuch, whom the Devil (who was the great Informer) hath made Lyars and Informers, Falſe Witneſſes and Falſe Accuſers againſt the Righteous; and let them be like ſo many Way-marks, to ſhun the Evil; but <hi>Chriſt is come to deſtroy the Devil and his Works, and to bruiſe his Head,</hi> who was the Informer againſt <hi>Job,</hi> and the Falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and Informer of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> to tranſgreſs the Command of God; therefore if Chriſt deſtroyeth the Father of all ſuch Informers, Perſecutors and Lyars, and Falſe Witneſſes, his Children may fear Deſtruction; and the Saints can ſing <hi>Halelujah</hi> over the Devil, Satan, Serpent, and all his Followers, that do his work, whom the Living God will Reward accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. FOX.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, Printed by JOHN BRINGHVRST, at the Sign of the Book in <hi>Grace-Church Street.</hi> 1682/3.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47476:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
